<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Great Britain's glory: being the history of King Arthur with the adventures of the Knights of the Round Table.</title>
            <author>J. S.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1697</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 58 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 14 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A62136</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S64</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R219789</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99831236</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99831236</idno>
            <idno type="VID">35699</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A62136)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 35699)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2040:31)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Great Britain's glory: being the history of King Arthur with the adventures of the Knights of the Round Table.</title>
                  <author>J. S.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[24] p. : ill. (woodcuts)  </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed by and for W.O. and sold by the booksellers,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[ca. 1697?]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Imprint date conjectured by cataloger; Wing reports "after 1695".</note>
                  <note>Title page woodcut.</note>
                  <note>"To the reader" is signed: J. S.</note>
                  <note>Caption title on A2r and running title read: The history of King Arthur.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-C⁴.</note>
                  <note>Pages stained, print faded.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Arthurian romances --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>Lauren Proux</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>Lauren Proux</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:35699:1"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Great Britains</hi> GLORY: BEING THE HISTORY OF King ARTHUR; WITH THE ADVENTURES OF THE Knights of the Round Table.</p>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>depiction of knights of the round table</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>
               <hi>London:</hi> Printed by and for <hi>W. O.</hi> and ſold by the Bookſellers.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:35699:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:35699:2"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:35699:3"/>
            <head>To the READER.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Courteous Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>DUring the Revolutions of this Kingdom ſuch have been the Valerous Exploits of the Princes, and other Renowned War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riours, Natives, not only in this our Land and neighbouring Countries, but throughout the known World, that all Nations have ſtood ama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed, and trembled at their Proweſs: And amongſt other, well may the Famous <hi>Arthur,</hi> that renown<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Britiſh King take place; though (to leſſen the Credit of his great Exploits) ſome envious Aliens have endeavoured to prove there was never ſuch a Man; but ſince it is evident by Chronologers of the moſt Antiquity, and Integrity, that he was the Son of <hi>Vter Pendragon,</hi> of the Ancient Britiſh Royal Blood, I ſhall not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> more Arguments to manifeſt it to the World <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> to the Matter of Hiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ory, as I ſign it layed down for the Inſtruction of future Ages; And remain, Reader,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Yours, to ſerve you, <hi>J. S.</hi>
                  </hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:35699:3"/>
            <head>The Hiſtory of King <hi>Arthur.</hi>
            </head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. I.</head>
               <head type="sub">Of the Parentage of King <hi>Arthur;</hi> with a Deſciption of his u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſual Accouterments; his Viſio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, and the Interpretation thereof; and how he conſtituted the Knights of the Round Table.</head>
               <p>THe Saxons after the departure of the Romans, having (under the title of Friendſhip) ſeized upon many ſtrong Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces in this Kingdom, the native Britains, after having tryed their Fortunes in many dreadful Battles, were obliged to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tire into <hi>Wales</hi> and <hi>Cornwal;</hi> yet retaining many Places of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable ſtrength: and from thence, by frequent Excurſions, they greatly annoyed the Enemy: not forgetting their antient Valour, and the former Glory of this Iſle, amongſt which was King <hi>Vter Pendragon,</hi> lineally deſcended from the Britiſh Kings, who in the Year, <hi>Anno 500,</hi> began to Reign over the Britains that poſſeſſed the Mountainous Country with great ſucceſs, giving the Saxons many Defeats, and gaining upon them; till at laſt, falling in love with a fair Lady named <hi>Igreyin,</hi> Wife to <hi>Alfridus</hi> Duke of <hi>Cornwal,</hi> he ſo doted on her Beauty, that not finding her to be won by perſwaſion to yield her Chaſtity to his Diſpoſal, he plotted with <hi>Merlyn</hi> a famous Necromancer of that Age, to bring his De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigns about by Policy. This Necromancer undertaking the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, the better to eaſe his Prince's labouring Thoughts, with Spells, and by Magick Inchantment, ſo wrought, that either de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luding the Lady's ſight, or transforming the King into the Shape of her Lord, ſhe received him as ſuch, and ſuffered him, in the ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of <hi>Alfridus,</hi> to enjoy her a whole night, on whom he got our famous <hi>Arthur:</hi> For her Lord being in War againſt the Weſt Sax<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, was ſlain e're his return; of which the King hearing, though greatly grieved at the loſs of ſo renowned a Subject, yet as much rejoyced that Fate gave him opportunity to procure the love of the fair Dutcheſs in an honourable way, which he proſecuting after the Days of Mourning were over, he ſo dealt with her by fair Words and rich Preſents, that being now at liberty, ſhe was contented to be his Wife, and was married to him by the Biſhop of <hi>Carlile,</hi> with great Pomp and Splendour; all the Lords and Nobles ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject
<pb facs="tcp:35699:4"/>to his Scepter together with their Ladies adorning their Nup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tials. and aſſiſting at the Ceremony: And ſo great was the Ioy, that Feaſting, Turnaments and all manner of Deſports to recreate the Senſes were held for twenty Days. Yet the Queen was trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled to find the Fruits of her Womb increaſe ſo faſt, as fearing to be ſuſpected of Adultry, for well ſhe knew ſhe had been deceived, when ſhe computed the time of <hi>Alfrydus</hi>'s Death with the ſame ſhe ſuppoſed him in her Embraces: but the King, to put her out of doubt, and to prevent melancholy thoughts, in loving wiſe revea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the whole Miſtery; yet it was agreed between them, that it ſhould be kept ſecret, and that the Child ſhould as ſoon as born, be conveyed to a truſty Guardian to prevent Coloquie. The Queen about ſix Months after the Ceremony of the Wedding was over, being brought to bed of a Son, the Child named <hi>Arthur,</hi> as it was reſolved, was conveyed by truſty Hands to a Lady of good Repute, named <hi>Mari<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>da,</hi> Wife to Sir <hi>Ector,</hi> one of the King's Knights; who brought him up in ſuch Learning as was meet for his Pears: When as his Father, worn out with the continual Folies of War, and much diſtempered through many wounds he had received, died, leaving him ſole Heir of his Dominions; who thereupon was pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claimed by moſt of the Nobility, and crowned King; tho' ſome taking the advantage of his green Years, rebelled, and raiſed di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers Commotions; but he growing up, and getting the Reins of Government into his Hands, did many great Exploits, as will in the Series of this Hiſtory appear.</p>
               <p>King <hi>Arthur</hi> by this time being grown up, became exceeding tall and ſtrong, inſomuch that he ſeemed more than Man, and in many Iuſts and Turnaments ſo well behaved himſelf, that none could ſtand before him: A Horſe he had which he called <hi>Beaucephalus,</hi> after the name of the Great <hi>Alexander</hi>'s Horſe; and he in all Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploits proved the beſt in the World: His Sword was of a large ſize, <hi>viz.</hi> five foot in length, and in breadth eight inches; cutting with two fearful edges, on which hung death and deſtruction: His Lance was eight Cubits, and the head thereof formed of maſſy Steel, weighing ſix Pound: His Armour was of the higheſt Prooff, ſhin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with Gems and burniſhed Gold: And the better to inure him to War and great Exploits, he frequently rode thus accutered; and often in places of greateſt danger, glorying in nothing more than his Strength and manly Proweſs, delighting in, nor fancying none but ſuch as were truly Valiant, and feared not Death in any of his dreadful Shapes; but to ſuch he was laviſh to Excceſs. Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining
<pb facs="tcp:35699:4"/>no other for his Counſellor, but <hi>Merlyn</hi> the famous Necro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mancer, from whom, as from an Oracle, he received the certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of future Events; and at his request recreated him with ſtrange and wonderful Sights, the Repreſentation of Magick; and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the reſt, upon a great Plain before the King's Palace, at <hi>Cardigan,</hi> he raiſed a ſtately Tower, and round it a pleaſant Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den adorned with Fruits and fragrant Flowers, Fiſh ponds. Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains, Bowers, and Vmbrages, into which he led the King and all his Nobility, feaſting them after a ſumptuous manner, as they imagined; but he had no ſooner reconveyed them thence, but look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing back, they ſaw all vaniſh in Thunder, Lightning, and a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digious Earthquake, to their great amazement; yet knowing be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it was but Defuſion, they reſted ſomewhat more ſatisfied, yet could not but think of what had paſſed. The day being ſpent in viewing this Piece of Recreation, end the King ruminating ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny things in his mind, at laſt laying him down upon his Couch, he fell into a ſlumber, and then dreamed that he was carried into a ſpacious Haſt, in which ſtood a Table of great circumference, out of the middle of which grew an Oak and Laurel, with Crowns, Scepters, Swords, and Enſigns hanging on them, and that they were guarded by many valiant Knights, high in Proweſs, and terrible to the whole World, which made him deſirous to become their Aſſociate; nor did he ſooner demand it, but they joyfully re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived him, and placing him in a Chair of Ivory and Gold, made him their Chief, and gave him a Banner with a Lyon rampant portrayed thereon; and this Motto written, viz. <hi>Ever Victorious;</hi> upon which, the ſound of Trumpets, noiſe of Drums, clattering of Arms, ſhouts and cries ſaluted his Ears: And he ſuppoſed he beheld Armies in rout and ſlaughter, ſcattered through the whole World, and that the Couquerers laid the Trophies at his Feet, and with an Vniverſal Shout ſaluted him, <hi>Great Monarch of the Weſtern World.</hi> At what time awakning, he found it but a Dream, yet revolving in his Mind the ſtrangeneſs of the Fancy, the next morning he related it to his Nobles, who aſſured him of hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py Preſages, and adviſed him to make inquiry into the Interprera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion thereof; whereupon, ſending for his Necromantick Counſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lor, he related it to him, who promiſed within a day to give him the ſignification of his Dream, which he did as followeth: <hi>viz.</hi> That by the Table was ſignified his Kingdom; by the Knights the Pillars and Strength thereof; by Oak and Laurel, Strength Victory and Durance; the Crowns, Scepters, Swords and En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigns,
<pb facs="tcp:35699:5"/>the Spoiles of the Nations he ſhould be poſſeſs's of; and the Schene of War, the Repreſentations of the many dreadful Bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tles he ſhould fight, wherein he ſhould ever remain victorious; and the making him Chief, giving him the Standard, and placing him in a Chair Ivory and Gold, denoted him deep in his Subjects Love, and that no Treaſon ſhould proſper againſt him This Interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation highly pleaſed the King, and raiſed his towring Imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations to ſuch a pitch, that he reſolved to ſpread the terror of his Arms throughout the World: Wherefore he made great Prepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of all manner of Warlike Proviſion, but above all of hardy and couragious Knights, inviting them from all parts to his Court; and for their better Incouragement, cauſed a ſpacious Hall three hundred Foot in length, and twenty in breadth, to be built, with Glaſs Turrets on the top, ceiled with Fret-work and Gold, wainſcoted with Cedar, and paved with Marble; in the midſt of which he placed a Round Table, at which four hundred Knights might ſit, and cauſed it daily to be furniſhed with great ſtore of choice Proviſion, for the entertainment of ſuch Men of War as would reſort thither; and ſhortly after conſtituted the Order of the Round Table, allowing a Yearly Penſion of a hundred Mark to ſuch as were truly valiant, and would intole themſelves to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend his Service when Occaſion required, making himſelf the Head Soveraign of the Order; ſo that by this means the valiant Men of the neighbouring Nations tendered their Service to him, and were admitted into the noble Order, but not before they had been proved in ſome Exploit.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. II.</head>
               <head type="sub">How King <hi>Arthur</hi> warred with the Kings of <hi>Mercia,</hi> and the <hi>Eaſt Angles,</hi> who invaded his Dominions, ſlew a Monſtrous Gyant, and put their Armies to the Rout, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THe King being eſtabliſhed in his Throne, and having thus far proceeded, cauſed a place to be made for Iuſting, where <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> every Week his Knights exerciſed in Martial Order, and Iuſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with each other; and to him that did heſt the King would fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently ſend one rich Preſent or other, himſelf being ſtill a Specta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor of thoſe Exerciſes, and at all great Feaſts preſent amongſt them at Dinner, having a Chair like a Throne placed on that part of the Table that was towards the upper-end of the Hall; but no Muſick ſuffer'd, except the Martial Sounds of Drums, Trumphers
<pb facs="tcp:35699:5"/>and Clarions, in which moſt of all our Heroick Prince delighted. And now being furniſhed with mighty Men, that might compate to <hi>David</hi>'s Worthies (if not exceed them) in dreadful Foots of Arms, he paſſionately deſired to have an honourable Occaſion to try his and their Valours, which was not long wanting; For the Mercian King of the Saxons, and the King of the Eaſt Angles, preſuming upon their Strength, broke into <hi>Cornwal,</hi> part of King <hi>Arthur</hi>'s Dominions, and committed divers Outrages, burning, plundring, raviſhing and ſlaughtering in ſuth a dreadful manner, that the People (with ſuch ſubſtance as they could con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vey) fled every-where before them: The News of which rouzed our Lyon-like Prince, who taking with him his Guard of Knights, and eight hundred common Soldiers, the Flower of his Dominions, by ſwift Marches paſſed on give War the meeting; whoſe approach to the Enemy (being treble the Number) little regarded, not doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to give him the Overthrow, truſting greatly to the force of one <hi>Cingeterox,</hi> a monſtrous Gyant, nine Cubits high ſix in circumference, and armed with a huge Battle are and Coat of Mael; but the undaunted Prince, whom Fear could not diſmay ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving animated his Soldiers, and ſet them in Battle-array attended by his Knights, broke through the Ramparts, killing ſuch as guard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the Camp, and ſetting upon the Infidels, for ſo at that time they were, cutting through the thickeſt of them, made ſuch a ſlaughter that all the way he paſſed was ſtrewed with dead Bodies; yet on he preſſed through lanes of Death, his Heroick Champions following, as animated by the Martial Deeds of their Renown<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Leader. Nor did they leſs annoy the Enemy, who by this time taking the Alarum in all parts, come running to oppoſe them, and began to make ſome ſlaughter of his Men, eſpecially where the Gy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ant fought; which the King perceiving, by the Cry that aroſe, cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed his Standard, with the great Lion to advance that way, bearing down all before him till he came to the place where he found <hi>Cinge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terox</hi> and <hi>Ethwaldus,</hi> the King, bathing their Ares in the Blood of his Men, of which they had ſlain three hundred, when as King <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thur</hi> with a loud voice cried, <hi>Turn this way, Infidels; ſpare the Weak, and bend your force again the Stronger.</hi> Vpon which, the Gyant ſtairing on him, with a dreadful voice replied, <hi>Who art thou that comes to ſeek thy Death? I am a Slodier,</hi> ſaid the King, <hi>and one that am come to fetch thy Head by way of Reprizal for the Miſchiefs thou haſt done in my Country. But you muſt get it firſt,</hi> ſaid the Gyant. <hi>That ſhall not be long,</hi> ſaid the King; and thereup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb facs="tcp:35699:6"/>charged on the Monſter ſo furiouſly with his Sword, that e're he could welld his Battle; oxe with a full ſtroke on his Helme, which made the ſire ſpring from thence, he made him ſtaggar three huge Paces, and bend with his Knee to the Ground; then the Gyant (inraged) made at him, and ſtruck at the King, ſo that the blow dazled him, and made his Eyes ſwim; but ſpon recovering, he that had never been ſo uſed before, reſolved revenge thereupon (af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter a fuſt ſtroke) wheeling his dreadful Sword about, he ſtruck the Monſter en the Helmet with ſuch force, that cutting it through, the Sword entred fix inches, whereupon, with a terrible groan, he fell to the Earth, and at what time the King ſtood on him and devided his Head from his Trunk, the which he delivered to his Eſquire that bore his Bow and Quiver. Nor were the Knights of the Order idle, for Sir <hi>Lancelot</hi> had by this time grievouſly wounded the Mercian King, and taken him Priſoner; and Sir <hi>Triſtrian</hi> ſlain thirty ſix Captains beſides thirty ſix common Soldiers; ſo that the King of the Eaſt Angles ſeeing all go to wrack, and his Men were diſordered, cauſed the Retreat to be ſounded; whereupon his Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains endeavoured to bring off their Men, but they being in great Conſternation, and the Britains preſſing on them, (fearful of death) fled in all parts, and left all the Booty they had gotten to the Conquerors, who fiercely purſuing the flying Foe, made ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible flaugheer, inſomuch that ſuch as could not fly into Caſtles and Strongholds fell by the Sword, to the number of twenty thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand. This Over<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>how being noiſed abroad, brought a great Fear upon all the Saxon Princes, ſo that the Mertians wholly ſubmit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and ſent a great Ranſom for their King; who upon his ſwear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to become Tributary and Vaſſal to King <hi>Arthur,</hi> was ſet at liberty. Nor were there any of their petty Kings that then poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed this Iſland which they had devided into Heptiarchey, but ſent their Ambaſſadors with great Preſents to intreat a Peace; the which upon their acknowledging him their Supream Prince, and paying eath two hundred Geldings, a Faulcon, and a Grey-hound year<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly was accorded to. And thus flouriſhed this Renowned King in the beginning of his Reign, but more dreadful and redoubted were his future Deeds, as by the Sequel will appear.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <pb facs="tcp:35699:6"/>
               <head>CHAP. III.</head>
               <head type="sub">How King <hi>Arthur</hi> paſſed into <hi>Denmark,</hi> conquered the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of <hi>Norway;</hi> overthrew <hi>Burnamiſſa</hi> the Daniſh King; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſieged <hi>Copen-Hagen;</hi> and how, at the Intreaty of <hi>Geneura,</hi> the Siſter of the Daniſh King, he hearkered to an Accord, and had an Interview with <hi>Burnamiſſa,</hi> and how a Peace was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded between them, upon the whole matter being left to the Princeſ's Award: and how King <hi>Arthur</hi> falling in Love with the fair Princeſs, married her.</head>
               <p>THe King having in a manner brought <hi>England</hi> to his ſubject<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ion, reſolved not to ſuffer the current of his Victory to be damed up with Eaſe, took counſel with <hi>Merlyn</hi> and the moſt valiant of his Knights, what Enterprize was next to be undertaken, who adviſed him, That it was moſt for his Honour to revenge the Injuries he had received by the Danes, who roaming about thoſe Seas, had not only taken divers of his Ships, but (landing) had ſurprized ſome ſmaſt Towns upon the Sea coaſt, and burnt them, corrying the Inhabitants into miſerable Captivity, and by ctuel Tortures obliged them to offer Sacrafice to their Idols, that King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom being then unconverted. This motion pleaſed the King, whoſe reſtleſs ſpirit and deſire of Glory made him impatient of eaſe; whereupon he cauſed a great Navy of Ships to be rigg'd in <hi>Milford</hi> Haven, and in all other Ports, and gave Order for the building Men of War and Gallies, ſo that in ſix Months ſpace he had a Fleet of ſmall and great Veſſels that conſiſted of three hundred Sail, on which early in the Spring he imbarqued with twenty eight thouſand choice Soldiers, and all manner of Warlike Proviſion; having by this time inroled twenty new Knights, to ſupply the places of ſuch as fell by the Sword or dyed of divers Diſeaſes; and ſo with a freſh gale weighing Anthor, and with a fair Wind arriving in the <hi>Baltick</hi> Ocean, entered the Straits, now guarded by the two famous Caſtles of <hi>Coronsburg</hi> and <hi>Elzeburg,</hi> the latter ſtanding on the Coaſt of <hi>Norway,</hi> and, there brought ſuch a fear on either Shore, that the Inhabitans in all parts fled with what they could moſt conveniantly carry, leaving the reſt for a prey to the Britains, who under the Conduct of their victorious King, intiched themſelves with a great booty; when incamping before <hi>Nidroſia</hi> in <hi>Norway,</hi> ſummoned the City to yield, but there being a ſtrong Gariſon therein they returned Anſwer, <hi>That they kept the City for</hi> Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>namiſſa,
<pb facs="tcp:35699:7"/>
                  <hi>King of</hi> Denmark, <hi>and would in no wiſe yi ld it with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out his Order:</hi> whereupon the King commanded the Aſſault to be made by twelve thouſand Men, under the leading of forty faut Knights of the order of the Round Table, who heving their Scaling Engines in a readineſs, on <hi>Eaſter-eve</hi> marched to the Wall, and with a ſhowre of Arrows and Wild-fire drdve the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fendants thence; when as Sir <hi>Ector,</hi> bearing the Royal Seand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ard, mounted, and making great ſlaughter of ſuek as oppoſed, cutting of Arms, Legs, and Helmed Heads, placed it on the chief Bulwark, which the reſt ſeeing, on all ſides ſfreve to imitate him, ſo within leſs than ſix hours the City was won, which the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quered perceiving, retired to the Marker-place, and throwing down their Arms begged Mercy; which the King generouſly granted; yet gave the Spoil of the City to the Soldiers, not reſerving any part to himſelf, which ſo heightned them, that (leaving a Gariſon there) paſſed on to <hi>Bergen,</hi> which upon the firſt Summons ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rendred; and by its Example all the remaining Cities and walled Towns did the like, ſo that the Kingdom of <hi>Norway</hi> was entirely at King <hi>Arthur</hi>'s Devotion: whereupon finding no more to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quer, he having received a ſupply of five thouſand Men to make up the number he brought, by reaſon he was forced to leave the like Number in Gariſon, imbarqued, and paſſed the Straits, landed upon the Dainiſh Shore, filling all with Terror and Amazement; when as that King having gathered a huge Army, advanced to give him Battle, which did not a little rejoyce King <hi>Arthur,</hi> who greatly deſired to try his ſtrength in Mar: when jayning, on the great Plain before <hi>Copen-Hagen,</hi> a dreadful Fight began; but Victory (who never declined our Heroick Prince) ſoon declared for the Britains, ſo that the Daniſh King Anding the Battle ſwerve, and that he could not ſtay his Men longer from open flight, to co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver their Shame, ſounded the Retreat; whereupon they retiring in great Confuſion, King <hi>Arthur</hi> and his Knights following ſo furiouſly, that all the Plain was ſtrewed with the bodies of the ſlain, and ſo hotly they preſſed on, that e're three parts of the Army en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered the City, the Gates were ſhut up, and a third pars ſhut out, for fear the Britains ſhould enter pell-moſt with them, who were by the furious Soldiers ſlain in the fight of their Friends, though the compaſſionate King bid ſpare the Sword.</p>
               <p>The Danes thus overthrown, the King intamped before the City, reſolving to carry it by force, and the next Day prepared for the Aſſault, reſolving to march in the head of his Knights to win
<pb facs="tcp:35699:7"/>immortal Fame by his planting his Srandard upon the Wall with his own Hands, or to loſe his Life; nor could the Peeſwaſion of his Nobles make him decline it: but as he approached the Wall, the Gates opened, whereupon he ſuppoſed the Foe intended to ſally, but inflead of armed Men, there iſſued out a Troop of beautiful Ladies, and in the front of them the beaureous <hi>Genura,</hi> Siſter to <hi>Barnamiſſa</hi> the Maniſh King, whereat King <hi>Arthur</hi> muth wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and commanding his Men to ſtand in Battalia with twelve Knights went to meet them, when as the Ladies approaching him, the fair and beauteous Princeſs fell at his Feet, and bedewing the Ground with Gears, beſought him to have Compaſſion on her diſtreſſed Country; the King being moved at this unuſual ſight, in loding wise raiſed her in his Arms, and bad her be of good Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort; bur the ſorrowful Lady, whom Tears made more lovely, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed all Comfort unleſs he would grant het Requeſt, to which the King (overcome by Tompaſſion) conſenced, after a ſhort Pauſe, if what the demanded might conſiſt with his Honour: whereupon opening a Casker that one of her Ladies held, the firſt preſented him with Iewels of great value ſet in Gold, and then intreated that an Interview might be had between him and her Brother; to which the King readily conſented, as already faeling Love's pointed Shafts pierce his high prooffed Armour, and preſenting the fair Princeſs with a Crown of Gold ſet with Pearls and Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, which he had taken in the Mercian War; as likewiſe her Ladie with Iewels of great price; he diſmiſſed them, and cauſed a royal Tent to be pitehed about a Furlong fram the Vaunt guard of his Army.</p>
               <p>Hoſtilities ceaſing, the Daniſh King with twenty of his chief Nobility came to King <hi>Arthur</hi>'s Tent, and there in humble wiſe would have proſerated themſelves, but the King would not permit it; but making them ſit down actorsing to their Degree, entered into a Diſcourſe with them, relating at large the juſtneſs of his taking up Arms and demanding Reſtitution for the Wrongs his Subjects hed received, and for the Miſchiefs his Country had ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtained; to which Burnawiſſa replyed, <hi>That whatever had hapned in that Nature, had been without his Knowledge; but however knowing him to be a Prince of great Clemency, he would be well contont to ſubmit to whatever he ſhould think fit:</hi> The King overcome by the meekneſs of the Dane, finding a relenting in his Breaſt, as generouſly offered to refer the whole marter to the beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous Princeſs, and bound himſelf to ſtand <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> what Award He ſhould
<pb facs="tcp:35699:8"/>make; which was joyfully accepted by <hi>Burnamiſſa,</hi> who expected be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, that no leſs than his Kingdom of <hi>Norway</hi> would make Satiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction to the offended Britiſh Monarch: whereupon the Princeſs was ſent for, who came, attended by divers Ladies of Honour, in moſt ſumptuous Attire, glittering in Gold and Fems, which were out-vied by her imcomparable Beauty; when making her Approach, King <hi>Arthur</hi> aroſe from his Chair of State and ſaluted her; as likewiſe his Knights did her Ladies: Then <hi>Burnamiſſa</hi> made her acquainted with the Pleaſure of King <hi>Arthur;</hi> but ſhe in Modeſty refuſed to be Arbitreſs in ſo weighty a matter, till the King preſſed it, and deſired her to do him ſo great an Honour; whereupon after ſome Conſideration ſhe awarded, That her Brother ſhould defray the whole Charge of the War, and reſtore all ſuch Ships as were found to appertain to any of King <hi>Arthur</hi>'s Subjects, and that the Offenders being taken ſhould be delivered to the King to diſpoſe of as he thought fit, and then the King to depart the Land, and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>draw his Garriſons. Theſe Articles were highly approved on either part, and the Princeſs her Wiſdom admired: whereupon Commandment was given to proclaim them with beat of Drum and sound of Trumpet, and that from thenceforth all Hoſtility ſhould ceaſe.</p>
               <p>Peace being thus happily accorded, the Danes rung their Bells and made Bon-fires in every City, all the Nobility feaſting their poor Neighbours and Tenants throughout the Kingdom; when as the Daniſh King cauſing a royal Pavillion to be reared with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the City, prepared a ſumptuous Feaſt, to which he in humble wiſe invited the King and his Nobles, and ſo great was the En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertainment, that the like had not been known before in that Kingdom.</p>
               <p>But what pleaſed King <hi>Arthur</hi> more than all, was the ſight of the fair Princeſs, with whom by this time he was moſt paſſionately in Love: Nor did the Feaver of his Deſire leſs afflict her, though ſhe durſt not raiſe her Hopes ſo high; till at laſt the King (not longer able to reſiſt the Magick of heri Eyes) took the opportunity of breaking his Mind to her, who humbly told him with a demure Countenance, <hi>That ſhe could not conceive herſelf worthy the Thoughts of ſo great a Monarch; but if it pleaſed him to conde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcend ſo low, as to raiſe her to ſuch Dignity, ſhe had no Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment againſt his Pleaſure, if her Brother would conſent.</hi> This pleaſing Anſwer overjoyed the King, inſomuch that ſending for the Daniſh King, he deſired to beg one Favour of him; <hi>Nay,</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied
<pb facs="tcp:35699:8"/>
                  <hi>Burnamiſſa, your Majeſty may command even what you pleaſe, ſince to your Clemency I owe ſo much.</hi> Then ſaid King <hi>Arthur, 'Tis this fair Pledge of laſting Peace that I with low Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion do requeſt. If my Siſter be contented,</hi> ſaid the King, <hi>I am overjoyed at what I hear, and have long deſired to be allyed unto ſo great a Prince, yet muſt not compel a free Mind. You need not,</hi> (ſaid the Princeſs, bluſhing like a Roſey Bloom that opens in <hi>June</hi> or <hi>July</hi> to the Morning-Sun) <hi>for I have already parted with that Heart that needs would go, upon Condition you conſented. I do conſent moſt willingly,</hi> replyed the King; and thereupon taking King <hi>Arthur</hi> in his right Hand, and the Princeſs in his left, he joyned their Hands, and at the Requeſt of the former, <hi>Segbert</hi> the Britiſh Arch-Biſhop Married them, according to the Cannons of the Britiſh Church, pronouncing many dreadful Cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes on whoever ſhould attempt to untye the ſacred Band. This known in the Camp and City, redoubled the Ioy, ſo that all Night long whole Loads of Pines blazed, inſomuch the Fires created a new Day as ſoon as <hi>Sol</hi> was ſet; and ſo ſumptnous was the Feaſt, which laſted many Days, that <hi>Rome</hi> in all her Glory could not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed it; the Martial Feats (to win Glory, and the Love of the Ladies) were ſo many that I have not place here to relate them.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. IV.</head>
               <head type="sub">How returning home, King <hi>Arthur</hi> ſound his Country invaded by <hi>Magor</hi> King of <hi>Ireland,</hi> and how he vanquiſhed him; and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving recovered the Iſle of <hi>Angle-Sea</hi> from the French, ſailed into <hi>France,</hi> to revenge the Injury done to his Subjects, over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throwing their Army. Alſo how Queen <hi>Geneura</hi> was delivered of a Son; and of the Preſents and Vows made by the Saxon Kings: With a full Deſcription of the Knights of the Round Table.</head>
               <p>THe King having been abſent from his own Dominions for the ſpace of ſix Months, began to caſt his Eye homeward; when having remitted <hi>Burnamiſſa</hi> the Charges he was at, and only gave order his Subjects Loſs ſhould be repaired, he with his fair Queen, whom the King leaded with rich Preſents, took leave of the Daniſh Court, and imbarquing with the whole Army, and divers of the Daniſh Nobility, who from chair King hed order to attend the Queen; having a fair gale, on the ninth of <hi>October</hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:35699:9"/>landed where they firſt imbarqued, and were received with univerſal joy; whereupon the King coming to a Caſtle of his, near <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>. feaſted the Dainiſh Nobility in a mast ſpianded manner. But whilſt he remained there, he had notice, That <hi>Magor</hi> King of <hi>Ierland,</hi> who by his Amiaſſaders had courted the fair <hi>Gemna,</hi> and been refuſed, was (to revenge it on his Arrival) landed with great Power in <hi>South Wales;</hi> whereupan the King comforting his Queen, who was greatly grieved that through her cauſe ſuch ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denly Troubles ſhould ariſe, paſſed on with his victorious Army, and gave him Battle near <hi>Merioneth,</hi> and utterly diſcomfited him, ſo that flying with his broken Army, and being every-where aſſaiſes by the Country Peaſants, who had laid the way for him, he ſcarcely eſcaped to his Ships with five thouſand out of his thirty thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand; ſo that King <hi>Arthur</hi> (ſpeedy as <hi>Ceſar</hi> in his victories) re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>turned to his fair Queen with the Trophies of his conquered E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies long before he was expected to have fought the Battle; when ſending four thouſand Men under the leading of Sir <hi>Lancelot</hi> and divers of her good Knighes, they landed on the Iſle of <hi>Angle-<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>,</hi> and drove thence the French that had for ſome time paſt, during the troubles of this Kingdom, ſetled themſelves there.</p>
               <p>The King's Victories daily increaſing, the Terror of his Name being ſpread wide, it made the moſt redoubted Monarch tremble; yet durſt <hi>France</hi> (then powerful at Sea) invade our Coait, and with fire and ſword ſpoiled many Sea-towns, carrying away great booty, as alſo the People, the Men they made cow in their Gallies. and the Women to ſatiate their prodigious Luſt; when as the crys of his ſuffering ſujects reaching his ear where he was delight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing himſelf with his Queen, he reſolved once more to forſake the Camp of <hi>Venus,</hi> and her ſoft Delighis, to court Fame and Glory in the Camp of <hi>Mars;</hi> whereupon having ſent to <hi>Lothario<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> for Reſtitution, and receiving rather ſcorns than a ſatisfactory anſwer from that imperious King, he made great proparations for the War, and had at that time twelve Sale of Ships ſent to his aid by his Brother of <hi>Denmark;</hi> when being in a readineſs with an Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my of thirty four thouſand, he coaſted the Country, and puning into the bay of <hi>Marſelies,</hi> with his ſhot of Arrows that flew like Haile, drove the defendants from the ſhore, on which himſelf with his own Standard firſt leaped, and ſtood like an inraged Lyon, though a thouſand that is flew round his Head, and many <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> from his glittering ſhield; but long it was not e're the valiant Knights of the Order (imſrating their Soveraign) thruſt their
<pb facs="tcp:35699:9"/>Ships to Land, and putting their Soldiers in Battle-aray, charged furiouſly upon the formoſt Battailian of the Enemy, lead by the Duke <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Vallois,</hi> ſo that being overſet, they retreated in great diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>order, and finding no place to be received, broke the Ranks of their Friends; when as the Duke <hi>De Nevers</hi> advanced with the right wing of Horſe to their ſuccour, but was ſo gauled with the ſhot of Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rows that the Horſes miſchiefet more the Riders than the Britains.</p>
               <p>In this Confuſion the King drawing out ſix thouſand of his choice Men, charged upon the diſordered Enemy with ſuch courage that he pierced their main Battle, making lanes of death where-ever he came, cutting off Arms, Heads and Legs, inſomuth that the Daniſh General <hi>Gironeus</hi> imitating him, the French Soldiers (routed in all parts) left their Commanders and fled, inſomuch that the ſlaughter of the Nobility was great, a Fare even incident to that Kingdom; nor would they truſt to the weak wall of <hi>Marſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies,</hi> but flying to <hi>Lyons</hi> and <hi>Paris,</hi> left that part of the Country naked, to be poſſeſſed of the Britains.</p>
               <p>The terror of this overthrow alarming the French Court, and finding that brought home to them which they had uſed to others a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad, the People with Tears beſought their King to appeaſe the Conquerer in time, and thereby prevent worſe deſolation, who con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering his tottering Kingdom was at ſtake, ſent four of his prime Lords to beg a Week's Ceſſation or Truce, to which King <hi>Arthur</hi> (whoſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> was more at Glory and Renown than Advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage) accorded, during which time, the King having raiſed a Miſtion of Crowns ſent them in divers Waggons, with other rich Preſents, to purchaſe his Peace, and the depatrure of his new come Gueſt, yet prevailed they not e're he had made his Acknowledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment for the indignity put upon the King's Ambaſſadors, and deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver the Town and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> Marſelies, to be poſſeſſed as a Pledge of future Peace by the Britains for the spare of twenty Years to come and upon pain of forfeiting it for ever, no Hoſtilities to be uſed by Lend, nor Depravations by Sea. Theſe Articles accorded, the Kin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> haſtened to his own Country with the greareſt part of his Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, leaving only <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> Solders in <hi>Marſelies;</hi> and having amply rewarded the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> diſmiſſed them.</p>
               <p>Vpon King <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> he found, to his unſpeakable joy, his fair Queen <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 words">
                     <desc>〈◊◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> a lovely Boy, who, by the Advice of Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyn, he nam<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d <hi>Conſtantius,</hi> thoſe Victories and great Exploits that Prophet for<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>, which after his Father's death, he ſucceeding him in his Throne, exactly came to paſs: and now the joy bring
<pb facs="tcp:35699:10"/>great throughout the Britiſh Dominisns, all the Saxon Kings came to King <hi>Arthur</hi>'s Court, then removed to the then flourſih<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing City of <hi>Hereford,</hi> and made their Homage, complementing him highly on his Marriage, and the birth of his Son, preſenting the Queen and Royal Infant with great Preſents, as Iewels, Gold, and fragrant Spice of <hi>Arabia,</hi> promiſing for them and their Heirs to be obedient to the Britiſh Stepter though before and after the Death of King <hi>Arthur</hi> they brake their Vaws, though to their great diſadvantage: For the young Prince (almoſt as ſucceſsful in War as his Father) graſped the Kingdoms of the Mercians and Eaſt-angles with ſo hard a hand, that during his Life, they could not wreſt them from him; but to our purpoſe. King <hi>Arthur</hi> being the chief Favourite of Fortune, and the eldeſt Son of Fame, began to enlarge the ſplendor of his Court, and increaſe the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of the Knights of the Round Table, in whom conſiſted his chief Strength, for ſcarce was there any one of them, but durſt en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counter ten ordinary Men hand to hand; and as he increaſed them, ſo he enlarged their Penſions, which drew the moſt Valiant of all Nations to ſerve him, though none were admitted before they were tryed: The habit they ordinarily wore, when without their Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour, was a Veſt lined with Sables, and on the back of it a red Croſs, and on their Thighs Cuſhes of higheſt proof; their Stock<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings were in the manner of Bugkins, and their Shoes of Camels<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>skin, the Hair appearing outward: on their Heads they wore Caps made of Seal-skins lined with Silk and Cotted: and about their neck Silk of divers colours; each of them in War carrying a dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Faulchion, a Battle-axe, a Bow and Quiver, a Launce, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſeverally allowed a Eſquire or Armour-bearer, who attended them in all Battles.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. V.</head>
               <head type="sub">How <hi>King Arthur</hi> upon the Relation of a Hermit, ſailed into the Holy Land, took <hi>Ioppa,</hi> overthrew <hi>Salmanezar,</hi> and took <hi>Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem,</hi> with what elſe happened remarkable on that occaſion.</head>
               <p>ABout this time King Arthur finding nothing worthy of his Sword at home, and altogether impatient of eaſe, ſtudyed how he might imploy it abroad, and whilſt he was muſing thereon, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Hermit in poor aray came to the Court, and filled it at once with pitty and deſire of revenge upon the diſmal Relation he made, which was, <hi>That the</hi> Turks <hi>and</hi> Sarazens <hi>had fallen upon</hi> Iudea <hi>and</hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:35699:10"/>Palatine <hi>with an Army of one million of Men, and made ſuch ſlaughter of the Chriſtians in thoſe parts, that ſuch that eſcaped were forced to fly into Rocks and Caves of the Earth, and there were either ſtarved to Death, or became a Prey to wild Beaſts: And that they had taken the Holy City of</hi> Ieruſalem, <hi>after thirty days Siege, and put almoſt all the Chriſtians they found therein to the Sword, polluting the Temple and Holy Sepulchre with their Heatheniſh Worſhip: As alſo, that they impailed the Patriarch alive for refuſing to worſhip</hi> Mahomer.</p>
               <p>This Story coming to the King's ear, he could not refrain from ſhedding tears, when ſending for the Hermit, in the preſence of his Nobles, he moſt ſtrictly examined him to all particulars, and finding he delivered nothing but what (as he ſaid) himſelf had been an Eye witneſs too; the King turning to his Lords, ſaid, <hi>Hear you this, my Lords, ſhall we ſuffer the Enemies of our Lord and Saviour thus to Triumph over the profeſſors of his Name?</hi> To which they with one Voice reply'd, <hi>That it was intollerable, and they were ready to venture their Lives and Fortunes in that Holy War, and in his Service.</hi> Whereat the King highly com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mending their Reſolutions, vowed by the Paſſion of his bleſſed Lord, whom thoſe Infidels defied and blaſphemed, he would not take pleaſure in any thing till he had faced thoſe barbarous Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and tryed his Fortune to free the Holy City from its Pol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution; and thereupon he ſent to all the neighbouring Princeſs for Aid, reſolving to ſet ſail in the Spring, it being now the mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle of <hi>Auguſt:</hi> He likewiſe lay'd double Taxes upon his own Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, and demanded double Tribute of the Saxon Princes, who did not ſo willingly pay it at that time as was expected, by reaſon moſt of them were unconverted, and therefore ſecretly rejoyced at the Proſperity of their Brother Infidels: But however the King raiſed a great Maſs of Money; and cauſed his Navy to be augmen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted; ſo that from <hi>France, Denmark,</hi> and other parts of <hi>Spain,</hi> ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving received fifty Ships of War, moſt of them manned with Vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luntiers of thoſe Nations, he with two hundred Sail, on board of which he had five thouſand Men, in the beginning of <hi>April</hi> weigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Anchor, and having a fair wind, coaſting <hi>France</hi> and <hi>Spain,</hi> he joyned likewiſe divers other Ships, who were ready to attend him, for the noiſe of this War had overſpread all all Chriſtendons; wher paſſing through the Straits into the Mediterenian Sea, he brought ſuch a fear upon the Sea towns, that the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> them fled with their ſubſtance to the Mountains, into which
<pb facs="tcp:35699:11"/>the Chriſtians entering, found yet ſome booty; but (deſirous to paſs on to Jeruſalem) the King ſailed to the Iſle of <hi>Cyprus,</hi> then governed by one <hi>Emanuel</hi> a Chriſtian, where having refreſhed his Arms, he again imbarqued, and ſailing through that tract of Seas, arrived at <hi>Joppa.</hi> a famous Sea: port, and the In-let of <hi>Palaſtine,</hi> whiche he found ſtrongly fortifled, as likewiſe <hi>Salmanezer</hi> King of the <hi>Turks</hi> incampes with a Hoſt of one million of <hi>Turks, Jews,</hi> and <hi>Sarazens</hi> about ſix miles from thence; yet landing his Men, he reſolved to beſiege the City, and by taking it, ſecure the Port; whereupon cauſing his Enginers to make divers batterings after the <hi>Roman</hi> faſhion, which under the favour of the night (notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding the Beſirged hurled down Wild: fire and ſtones in grear a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundance) they ſer to the Walls on the North ſide, and by force of Cords battered with ſuch fury, that they rent the Vamures in di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers places, making the City tremble, which ſo alarum'd the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidels, that they ſallyed ten thouſand ſtrong upon the quarter, guarded by the Earl of <hi>Merioneth,</hi> but coming to handy ſtrokes, were forced to retire five thouſand lefs than they came; and the next morning, by King <hi>Arthur</hi>'s expreſs Command, a furious Aſſault was given on all parts, when as the Britains with their ſhot of Arrows bearing the Beſieged from their defences, mounted and planted the King's Standard upon the wall, entering and kiſſing the Infidels in great number, ſo that all the ſtreets ran Blood, till ſuch time as the King (upon their throwing down their Arms, and on their knecs brgging Mercy) bid ſpare the Sword; when having expeſled them the Town, he placed a Gariſon of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers Nations therein, and marched to joyn Battle with <hi>Salmane<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zer.</hi>
               </p>
               <figure/>
               <pb facs="tcp:35699:12"/>
               <p>The Victory thus happily gained, the Chriſtians found ſuch ſtore of Treaſure in the Tams, that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> was wounderful, the which the King ſharing amongſt his Sowiers, according as every and had deſerved, and well refeeſhed his Army, ſending the Mound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of his pare to <hi>Ioppa,</hi> and burſed the Slain; he with Banners ſpread marched towards <hi>Iernſalem,</hi> bringing a great fear on all the Cities in his way, muſt of which ſurrendred upon the firſt Sum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons; ſo that coming before the Holy City, whither the greateſt part of the ſcatrered Army was retired, he having ſummoned the Infidels to yield and ſave their lives, but receiving no anſwer, he batrered it with his Rams, War wolfes, and other fearful En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gines, till a part of the wall on the South ſide fell, upon which a furious Aſſault was given, inſomuch, that the Inſidels having drawn their greateſt ſtrength to defend <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> breach, a great ſlaughter was made; yet the Thriſtians reſolving to carry the City, which then was but ſmall, and very ravenous, preſſed on with ſuth vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, that the fearful Enemy being over-born, were every-where ſlain; and the Chriſtians enteing, plated King <hi>Arthur</hi>'s Stand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ard upon the Bulwarks, which ſo diſmayed the Infidels, that ſuch as could, fled by the Poſterns, and over the Brock <hi>Cedron,</hi> others hid themſelves in Caves till the fury of the Soldiers were over, and ſuch is could not do either, fell for the moſt part by the Sword.</p>
               <p>This famous City, being the firſt time thus taken by the Chriſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ians, a great number of miſerable Men and Women weré releaſed out of Dungeons, who had for a long time been fed with Bread of Affliction, half ſtarved, and miſerably uſed by the Infidels, for publikly owning the Name of the Lord, who, not far from thence, purchaſed them with his precious Blood to their unſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Ioy.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. V.</head>
               <head type="sub">How, upon notice that the <hi>Saxons</hi> invaded his Country, he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truned; and how upon his return, the <hi>Saxon</hi> Kings laied down their Arms: Alſo how King <hi>Arthur</hi> built many Religious Hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, and gave great Largeſſes to the Poor; and how he ſwore his Nobles and Knights to his Son <hi>Conſtantius,</hi> and ſo died.</head>
               <p>THe King having thus performed his vow, repaired the Walls; buit a ſtrong Caſtle, and placed ſeven thouſand Soldiers therein, beſides the Chriſtians of <hi>Syria</hi> and <hi>India,</hi> that daily flock<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed thither in great number; he received notice, that the <hi>Saxon</hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:35699:13"/>petty Kings in his abſence had caſt off his Allegience, and being united, invaded his Country inſomuch that his Queen, Son, and thoſe that he has left in charge with the Kingdom, being o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verchrawn in a ſpirited Battle were fled to the ſoftneſſes of <hi>Snow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>down</hi> Mounains. Which News greatly perplexed the King; ſo that having made his Offering at the Holy Sepuchre, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituted Religious Men to keep it, he with three parts of his Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my he brought, returned to his Ships, the other part being either ſlain in the Battle, peti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>ed by ſickneſs, or left in the Gariſon; yet e're he could <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>, twenty ſeven thouſand, <hi>Turks, Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>razens,</hi> and <hi>Aegiptians,</hi> lying in ambuſh in a Wood for that pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, fell upon the Rear of his Army, and cut off three or four hundred Britans and Danes e're the King with the Groſs of his Battle could draw up to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>eir relief; yet fatal was it to the Infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dels; for being unexpectedly incloſed by the Chriſtians, who fetch'd a compaſs behind divers littly Hills, they were almoſt all of them cut off.</p>
               <p>This ſecond Overthrow given the King quictly imbarqued his Soldiers, and ſailing by divers Iſlands, deſtroyed the Eariſons poſſeſſed by the Infidels: When one day going on ſhore on the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentory of <hi>Carthage,</hi> with a few of his Knights, he was ſet up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on by four hundred <hi>Moors,</hi> who ſallyed out of <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> is;</hi> but ſuch was his and his Knights invincible Courage, that they drawing their Swords, ſlaughteren the Barbarians in ſuch manner, that they fled with great crys, raking them to be more than mortal; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon the King cauſing eight thouſand Men inſtantly to come on ſhore deſieged the City, and with Wild ſice burnt it about the Batha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rians Ears, putting many of them to the Sword: And then march<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing up farther into the Country, there come againſt them ſix huge Lyons, bred in the Muritatian Forreſt, with whom the King and twenty of his Knights encountering, killed tweive, and put the other four to flight.</p>
               <p>King <hi>Arthur,</hi> impatient of ſtay, leaſt whilſt he conquered a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad his Country ſhould ſuffer with great ſpoyl put again to Sea, and ſayiing homeward, met with a Fleet of Dyrates. who taking his Ships for Merchams, ſet upon the foremoſt Souardran with loud Souts, caſting great quantity of ſtones and Wild-fire a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt them, but coming to graple, they ſoon found their miſtake, and then in vain endeavouring to fly, were miſerable ſlaughte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, inſomuch, that out of thiety but five eſcaped: In theſe Ships many miſerable Chriſtian Captives, both Men and Women, were
<pb facs="tcp:35699:13"/>found, of which the King taking compaſſion, ſent them into their reſpective Countries, allowing them all things neceſſary for their maintenance during the ſpace of a year, and ſo paſſed on towards his own Country.</p>
               <p>The King's approach being known to the <hi>Saxon</hi> Princes (who not long before had news that he was dead in the Holy Land, and thereby were animated to take up Arms) ſo diſcouraged them, that withdrawing their Forces, every one retired into his own Province, to ſludy how to appeaſe the Victorious Monarch, whom they had juſtly incenſed by their perſideons Treachery, and as ſoon as they had norice the King was landed and preparing his Forces to War againſt them, they ſent their reſpective Deputies with rich Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſents, to excuſe their raſh and unadviſed actions, promiſing never for the future to tranſgreſs in the like nature; yet the King being highly incenſed, would at no cheaper a rate paſs over their perſlde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous dealings, than a perſonal acknowledgment, and the ſum of two thouſand Marks each: As to be the better aſſured of them for the future, that each of them ſhould ſend his Son Hoſtage, and that thoſe that had no Sons, to ſend their neareſt Kinſmen. and over and above, to make reparation for ſuch damages as could be by any of the King's Subjects proved to be ſuſtained by their unlawful Arms. This being performed, a Peace enſued, and the King diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſed his Auxiliaries with great Rewards.</p>
               <p>King <hi>Arthur</hi> now having <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> to repoſe in Peace, and think and think on his many wonderful Deliverances, reſolved to apply his mind to deeds of Piety, and thereupon cauſed many Mona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtries and Religious houſes be built giving yearly maintenance to divers poor People, but eſperſally to ſuch as had lived in ſplen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dor, and were fallen to decay: And daily he viſteed the Sick, gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving them Chriſtian Comfort: and uſing his utmoſt endeavour to theriſh Learning and Arts, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> which ended his proper charge he built likewiſe many Schools <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Colledges giving himſelf wholly up to the ſtudy of the ſeven Liverall <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>; and ſo well pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fited he therein, that he became the greateſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> therein of his Age: But moſt of all, he fixed his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> upon his latter end, and with <hi>Solomon</hi> was frequently heard to ſay, <hi>All World<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly things were but Vanity and Vexation of Spirst; and that on Earth no real nor ſubſtantial joys were to be found.</hi> When in the ſixeth Year of his Age, and the forty ninth Year of his Reign, ſalling ſick, and by the opinions of his Phyſicians not likely to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover, he ſent for all his Nobles, and the Knights of the Order,
<pb facs="tcp:35699:14"/>and he cauſed them to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> fealty to his Son <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> in the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> wiſe and thereupon, finding <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> pious Expreſſions, and Prayers, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> his Nobles to be careful of ſecuring his Son in his Throne, and having great re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect to his Queen. he gave up the Ghoſt, to the great grief of his Subjects, but more of his fair Queen, who took it ſo grievouſly, that ſoon after fading into a Feaver, ſhe died, and was buried with him in a Monaſtery, built by him at <hi>Monmouth,</hi> whoſe tomb (richly adorned) continued viſible till the Diſſolution of the Fabrick in the time of <hi>Henry</hi> the Eight.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="authors_note">
               <l>Thus, Friendly Reader, I've <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ere,</l>
               <l>King <hi>Arthur</hi>'s Noble Acts, which doth appear</l>
               <l>More fully in the larger ten Sheet Book</l>
               <l>If thou therein, will caſt a friendly Look.</l>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            </div>
            <pb facs="tcp:35699:14"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
